Matrix multiplication is really
矩阵乘法运算非常实用
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
useful since you can pack
因为你可以通过矩阵乘法
a lot of computation into just
将大量运算打包到
one matrix multiplication operation.
一次矩阵的乘法运算中
But you should be careful of how you use them.
但是怎样使用这个方法你要提起注意
In this video I want to
在这个视频中 我想
tell you about a few properties of matrix multiplication.
介绍一些矩阵乘法的特性
When working with just raw
运算时 如果仅仅使用实数
numbers or when working with
或者说是标量
scalars, multiplication is commutative.
乘法是可以交换的
And what I mean by that is
我的意思是说
if you take three times
如果你用3乘以5
five, that is equal
那么这个运算等同于
to five times three and
5乘以3
the ordering of this multiplication doesn't matter.
这个乘法运算中两个量的顺序不重要
And this is called the commutative
这就是实数乘法
property of multiplication of real numbers.
的交换律
It turns out this property that
通过这个定律
you can, you know, reverse
你能够颠倒
the order in which you
乘法运算中变量的顺序
multiply things, this is not true for matrix multiplication.So
但是这不能应用在矩阵乘法中
concretely, if A and
所以 具体来讲 如果变量A和
B are matrices, then in
B是矩阵 通常情况下
general, A times B is
A乘以B
not equal to B times
不等于B乘以A
A.  So just be careful of that.
因此应该注意到这一点
It's not okay to arbitrarily reverse
随意颠倒矩阵
the order in which you are multiplying matrices.
乘法的顺序是不可行的
So, we say that matrix multiplication
因此 我们说 矩阵乘法
is not commutative, it's a fancy
是不可交换的，这是一个奇特
way of saying it.
的说法
As a concrete example, here
举一个具体的例子
are two matrices, matrix 1100
有两个矩阵 矩阵[1100]
times 0020, and if you multiply
乘以[0020] 如果你将
these two matrices, you get this result on the right.
这两个矩阵相乘 你会得到右边的结果
Now, let's swap around the order of these two matrices.
现在 让我们左右交换这两个矩阵的顺序
So, I'm going to take these
我们对这两个
two matrices and just reverse them.
矩阵 仅仅交换了一下位置
It turns out if you multiply
结果呢 你对这两个
these two matrices, you get
矩阵相乘的时候 你在右边得出了
the second answer on the
第二种答案
right and, you know, real
你看 很明显
clearly, these two matrices are
这个矩阵不同于
not equal to each other.
之前的结果
So, in fact, in
所以 事实上
general, if you have
在通常情况下 如果你
a matrix operation like
做一个矩阵运算
A times B. If A
比如A乘以B 如果
is an m by n matrix
A是一个m×n的矩阵
and B is an by
B是一个n×m的矩阵
M matrix, just as an example.
以此举例
Then, it turns out
这样 结果表明
that the matrix A times
矩阵A乘以B
B right, is going
会得到
to be an m by
一个m×m
m matrix, where as
的矩阵 当情况是
the matrix b x a
矩阵 BXA
is going to be an n
的时候会得到一个n×n的矩阵
by n matrix so the
所以
dimensions don't even match, right,
结果中即使是矩阵的维度都不相同 好吧
so A times B and
所以矩阵A乘以B和
B times A may not even be the same dimension.
B乘以A可能得到不相同的维度
In the example on the left,
在左边的例子中
I have all two by two matrices,
我有使用的都是2×2的矩阵
so the dimensions were the same,
这样的维度是相同的
but in general reversing the
但是通常情况
order of the matrices
交换矩阵顺序
can even change the dimension
会改变结果维度
of the outcome so
因此
matrix multiplication is not commutative.
矩阵乘法是不服从交换律的
Here's the next I want to talk about.
这是我接下来要讲的
So, when talking about real
所以当谈到实数
numbers, or scalars, let's
或标量的时候 请看
see, I have 3 times 5 times 2.
我用3×5×2.
I can either multiply 5
我也可以先用5
times 2 first, and
乘以2
I can compute this as 3 times 10.
然后用3乘以10
Or, I can multiply
再或者 我可以将
three times five for us and
3乘以5
I can compute this as, you
我可以这样计算
know fifteen times two and
再用15乘以2
both of these give you the same answer, right?
这两种算法得到了相同的答案 对吧？
Each, both of these is equal
这两个方法 都等于30
to thirty so Whether I
所以 无论
multiply five times
先用5乘以2
two first or whether I
或者
multiply three times five
先用3乘以5
first because well, three
都是因为
times five times two
3乘以5再乘以2
is equal to three times
都等于3乘以
five times two.
5再乘以2
And this is called the
这就是 所谓的
associative property of role number multiplication.
数乘的结合律
It turns out that matrix multiplication is associative.
事实证明 矩阵乘法也符合结合律
So concretely, let's say
因此 具体来说
I have a product of three
做三个矩阵的乘积
matrices, A times B times
矩阵A乘以矩阵B再乘以
C. Then I can
矩阵C.然后我就可以
compute this either as A
A乘以
times, B times C
B×C
or I can compute this as
或者可以计算
A times B, times C
A×B 再乘以C
and these will actually give me the same answer.
这将给出相同的答案
I'm not going to prove this, but
我不做这个运算的证明 但是
you can just take my word for it, I guess.
我想你可以把我的话记下来
So just be clear what I mean by
所以只要通过这两种情况明白我的意思
these two cases, let's look
就行了 让我们来看看
at first one first case.
第一种情况
What I mean by that is
我是说
if you actually want to compute
如果你要计算
A times B times C, what
A×B×C
you can do is you can
你可以通过
first compute B times C.
先计算B矩阵和C矩阵的积
So that D equals B time
这样D等于B×C
C, then compute A times
这时候计算A×D
D.  And so this is really
事实上这就是
computing a times B
A×B×C
times C.  Or, for
或者是
this second case, You can
第二种情况下
compute this as, you can
你可以这样计算
set E equals A
设定E等于A×B
times B.  Then compute E
然后计算
times C.  And this
ExC
is then the same as a
这就等同于
times B times C
A×B×C
and it turns out that both
结果表明
of these options will give
这两种选择
you, is guaranteed to give you the same answer.
都能保证给出相同的答案
And so we say that matrix
所以说矩阵乘法
multiplication does enjoy the associative property.
能够服从结合律
Okay?
好吧？
And don't worry about the terminology
同时不用担心术语
associative and commutative that's
结合律和交换律
why there's not really going to use
因为在这个课程后面的讲解中
this terminology later in these
不会使用这些术语
class, so don't worry about memorizing those terms.
不必担心这些条条框框
Finally, I want to
最后 我想告诉大家的
tell you about the identity
是单位矩阵
matrix, which is special matrix.
一种特殊的矩阵
So let's again make the
因此 我们再次类比
analogy to what we know
之前用到的实数的情况
of raw numbers, so when dealing
当处理
with raw numbers or scalar
纯数字或标量的时候
numbers, the number one,
数值1时
is you can think
你可以认为
of it as the identity of multiplication,
它是一个乘法单位
and what I mean by that
我用1的意思是
is for any number
对于任何实数Z
Z, the number 1
数字1
times z is equal
乘以Z
to z times one, and
等于Z乘以1
that's just equal to
它们的结果
the number z, right, for any raw number.
对于任意实数都是右面的Z
Z. So 1 is
因此1是
the identity operation and so it satisfies this equation.
一个单位操作 而且它满足这个等式
So it turns out that
事实就是
in the space of matrices as
在矩阵空间
an identity matrix as well.
它就是一个单位矩阵
And it's unusually denoted i,
通常它记作I
or sometimes we write it
有时我们把它记作
as i of n by
n×n的矩阵i
n we want to make explicit the dimensions.
以明确标出矩阵的维度
So I subscript n by n
所以下标写作n×n的时候
is the n by n identity matrix.
是指n行n列的单位矩阵
And so there's a different identity
这是不同单位矩阵
matrix for each dimension n and are a few examples.
在不同维度n中是不一样的 这里有一些例子
Here's the two by two identity
这是一个2×2的单位矩阵
matrix, here's the three
这个是3×3的
by three identity matrix, here's the four by four identity matrix.
这是4×4的
So the identity matrix, has the
所以单位矩阵
property that it has
的特性就是
ones along the diagonals,
沿对角线都是1
right, and so on and
等等
is zero everywhere else, and
其他位置都是0
so, by the way the
所以顺便提一下
one by one identity matrix is just a number one.
1×1单位矩阵就是个数字1
This is one by one matrix
这是一个1×1矩阵
just and it's not a very
它不是非常有意思的单位矩阵
interesting identity matrix and informally
它比较非正式
when I or others are being
我和多数人对这个矩阵都感到比较模糊
sloppy, very often, we will
更多情况下
write the identity matrix using fine notation.
我们使用更明确的符号表示
I draw, you know, let's
我划出来
go back to it and just write 1111,
回到这里 写1111
dot, dot, dot, 1
点 点 点 1
and then we'll, maybe, somewhat
这样也许一定程度上
sloppily write a bunch of zeros there.
拖泥带水写了一堆零在这里
And these zeros, this
这些零
big zero, this big zero
大零 大零
that's meant to denote that this
这意思是表示
matrix is zero everywhere except for
这个矩阵到处是零
the diagonals, so this is just
除了对角线上
how I might sloppily write
这就是比较拖沓的写法
this identity matrix
写这个单位矩阵
She says property that for
这说明一个特性
any matrix A, A times
对于任何矩阵A A乘以
identity i times A
单位矩阵I
A. So that's a lot
乘以A
like this equation that we have up here.
这就跟举得这个等式非常相像
One times z equals z times
1×Z等于Z×1
one, equals z itself so
结果是Z本身
I times A equals A
I×A等于
times I equals A.  Just
A×I
make sure we have the dimensions right, so
只要确保它们有相同的维度
if A is a n
所以如果A是一个n×n
by n matrix, then this
的矩阵
identity matrix that's an
单位矩阵就应该是
m by n identity matrix.
n×n维度
And if A is m by
如果A是m×n矩阵
n then this identity
那么单位矩阵
matrix, right, for matrix
使矩阵乘法
multiplication make sense that has a
有意义  就需要一个
m by n matrix because
m×n矩阵
this m has a match
因为使这个m匹配
up that m And
上一个m
in either case the outcome
在任何情况下
of this process is you
这个过程的结果是
get back to Matrix A, which
你的到的结果A
is m by n.
维度是m×n
So whenever we write
任何时候我们写
the identity matrix I, you
单位矩阵I
know, very often the dimension rightwill
它所暗含的维度
be implicit from the context.
是从上下文中得到的
So these two I's they' re
对于这两个矩阵
actually different dimension matrices, one
它们有不一样的维度
may be N by N, the other
一个是n×n
is M by M But when
另一个是m×m
we want to make the dimension
我们想要
of the matrix explicit, then sometimes
明确矩阵维度 有时候
we'll write to this I subscript
我们需要在下标中写出
N by N, kind of like we have up here.
n×n 跟前面的一样
But very often the dimension will be implicit.
但很多时候维度是隐含的
Finally, just want to point
最后要指出的是
out that earlier I
之前我提到
said that A times B
A乘以B
is not in general equal
通常并不等于
to B times A, right?
B乘以A 对不对？
That for most matrices A and B, this is not true.
对于大多数矩阵A和B 这是不成立的
But when B is the identity matrix, this does hold true.
但是B是单位矩阵的时候这不成立
That A times the identity
A乘以单位矩阵
matrix does indeed equal to
等于
identity times A, it's
单位矩阵乘以A
just that this is not true
这对于其他矩阵
for other matrices, B in general.
B 一般是不成立的
So that's it for the
这是
properties of matrix multiplication.
基于矩阵乘法的特性
And the special matrices, like the
特殊矩阵 诸如
identity matrix I want to
单位矩阵 等
tell you about, in the next
我会在接下来线性代数综述
and final video now linear algebra review.
的视频中讲到
I am going to quickly tell you
我会尽快讲解
about a couple of special
一些特殊
matrix operations, and after
矩阵运算
that you know everything you need
之后你将了解到
to know about linear algebra for this course
这门课程中你需要具备的解线性代数知识